[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
oh boyo alert boys and girls
welcome welcome welcome to the stoa i'm
peter limberg the steward of the stoa
and the stow is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most
at the knife's edge of this very moment
and we got everyone's favorite bad boy
from ireland
uber boyo um if you're not familiar with
who uber boyo is he runs a popular
youtube channel where he talks about
young michi
and jordan peterson and adjacent topics
like collective
consciousness and individuation and
shadow work and good stuff like that
he also has a coaching practice um where
helps people manage their anxiety and
improve creativity
and learning emotional intelligence how
um
this fine gentleman got on my radar is i
think alexander bart
introduced us via email and then we had
a few calls that we hit it off
uh and we've been trying to kind of like
go on each other's podcast for a while
so i thought
let's just get two birds with one stone
you come to the stowa and you repost it
on your channel talk about whatever you
want to talk about
so how today is going to work for those
of you familiar with the stoa
uber boyo is going to share his thoughts
on the the topic
uh at hand which is the pandemic of
groupthink
and then um would be around uh 10 20
minutes
and if you have any questions throughout
throw them in the chats right now have
put queue or question and then have your
question i'll call on you uh you'll meet
yourself ask your question to uberboyo
if you want me to read this on your
behalf because this will go on youtube
um
indicate that i'll read on your behalf
that being said
how are you doing my friend
oh you're mute all right i'm on mute
with now am i good
hello how was the crack what is
happening thank you very much for the
lovely introduction your your song
nearly lulled me into a trance i was
actually standing on your stuff that
the irish instincts kicked in i was like
i should just start drinking and dancing
now who knows
i'm sort of turned into the the token
leprechaun hello jeff how was the crack
um so would you like me to rock in and
sort of talk about what i was thinking
about talking about today or how would
you like
me to go about things yeah i think it'd
be best just to jump into it and then
uh uh just cue up your question in the
chat when you're um
listening sweet well a lot of people
probably know me
because i'm talking about mr carlos
young the famous
guy that jordan peterson always talked
about and everybody everybody sort of
like heard about young before and what
and then maybe the part that kind of
sticks with my channel the most is the
the notion of the the red book and this
this kind of
because nietzsche has his thoughts
spokesarathusha it's a very prestigious
book
i remember when i went to read the style
thruster it was like one of those things
that i built myself up to and there's
all this
anticipation going into it it's like oh
it's the great book and all this and
young has the red book as well
and it's quite different from almost
everything else he does because it's not
that um
intellectual it's it's very uh you could
say it's going down the artistic route
and that's perhaps the thing that i hit
on the most is the sort of creative
side of all this type of stuff and what
it means to be an artist and then
that red book and what that means and
everything that's wrapped up in that i
it's only came out like 10 years ago by
the way he kept it away for
until 2009 is when it got published he
actually died before it was like
released to the public
and um i've always wondered why people
why there's so much allure to it like
the way with nietzsche's zarathustra why
is there so much allure
with this book like what's going on why
do we why do we give it so much gravity
why is it so scary when you're walking
up to it and
and of course young's read book well the
story behind it is that he
he goes schizophrenic he goes psychotic
he goes mad he basically starts hearing
voices you know
the last thing you want to start hearing
is voices in your head that are not
yours and he starts to
he gets the whole issue buying things
starts showing up and and yeah someone's
saying the black books are coming out as
well that's an important thing but the
things are coming up in his head and and
uh speaking to him and you're kind of
thinking yourself
what the hell is going on here and he he
he of course
being a psychologist was like all right
i'm going i'm doing a crazy man i'm
going absolutely mad something bad is
happening here
and then i find this kind of a difficult
thing to interpret i don't think anybody
has really got an interpretation on this
that's
really wrestled it down to make sense of
it at all but the more i've dug into it
the more i've started to see that i
think
young hit upon something here that was
incredibly important for shall we say
the nature of the west or whatever we
call it ourselves or the place that we
are right now and
sitting in the middle of a massive
mental health crisis as we are
and a poster-industrial society where
pretty much everybody is unhappy and
getting involved with uh some very very
uh interesting outlets for their their
rage
is uh perhaps somewhere you could start
looking but of course young
doesn't have a good reputation despite
the fact that he is a prestigious one
maybe among people like jordan peterson
he's actually seen as a quack
he's seen as a quack by quite a lot of
the people in psychology
and um i remember this distinctly
because i had a friend who
wanted to do cognitive science and he
wanted to specialize in young and he
actually
said it to all these people on the board
who are going to take him in
and they all laughed well not laugh but
you know they sort of kind of like
rolled their eyes
when young's name came up this is
someone who's not actually taken serious
in the big bad world of academia and you
know
you would probably expect me to come
here and say to you
oh no okay young's actually a badass and
all that but i'd actually agree with
them to some extent like i guess
in order to possess young to really do
him justice you might have to risk
destroying him this is actually kind of
a scary thing because
what happened after young was the advent
of neuroscience hard neuroscience
and what a lot of young's theories are
are like very intuitive
descriptions of what he discovered and
what you notice is that the quote
unquote the jungians and i'm going to
kind of rag on people here a little bit
is that it it sort of it feels like a
replacement religion like the way the
christians would always talk about jesus
and
and even morality in the bible and all
that you notice this when people get
into young it turns into this sort of
set of jargon instead of sort of a set
of like cult-like behavior and all this
type of stuff and it's like my shadow my
anima and all this type of stuff and
there's this
weird and it's a very human thing this
weird grabbing this ability to grab
the um the words and think that you
possess the experience is what i'm going
to roll with here
and so a lot of the neuroscience comes
up and and people all start to go that
direction the more hard approach to
psychology
because psychology doesn't have a great
reputation for being a hard science
if you look at the replication crisis
you you will kind of understand why
these people
in the academics they're very very
nervous about what's going on with
psychology because it's all it seems an
awful lot like
the more you look into it and so young
gets thrown out with that and
of course if if we are to be serious and
we actually want to resurrect young in
some sense or even discover
if he's truthful we have to risk
destroying him and of course the red
book then
becomes very problematic because the red
book starts to show itself
as a man going insane a man with
schizophrenic delusions and if we're
going to be you know serious scientists
and
and really like study the knowledge and
all that it's it's not doing his case
very good you know it's kind of like
this is due to what serious problems it
looks like that type of thing
and so that kind of puts us in a bad
spot it kind of looks like young was a a
blip in the past the kind of like thing
that we got caught up when everybody was
taking lsd in the 60s and it's kind of
over now and it's like all right maybe
jordan peterson gave it a blip again but
it's probably going to
drift away but of course i don't think
so i don't think so fully and the reason
why i say that is because i think
neuroscience has gotten to the point now
where we are actually in a place where
we could start revisiting young in a
serious way and i've never seen jordan
do this by the way
i've the only person i've seen do this
is perhaps ian mcgill chris we're going
to talk about this a little bit
so there's a really the most fundamental
thing you'll notice about the brain
when you check out a brain is that it's
cut in half it's split in two there's
two
parts there's two big parts of the brain
and of course if we're gonna like try to
figure out what the brain does this
giant division in the brain is seriously
something we should start asking
ourselves like does the brain just do
that randomly or is there a point
now what it turns out is that there's
actually a massive point to this
and so much so that animals that are
less of less evolved
other animals that you say don't use
their brains as sophisticated as we do
and have don't don't have this split
as significant as we do so there's also
this suggestion that the brain split
in us is actually key to what makes us
you know human if you will
and the main thing about these brains
but the way we've evolved and
the advancement of the human brain split
is that actually the more evolved we are
the more that they sort of
don't talk to each other so it seems
like they've both got two different
roles
and they need to turn one off in order
to do their role and then it switches
the other on to do it's its role all
right this is the the left hemisphere
right hemisphere i'm going to use the
short hand of saying left brain right
brain people get mad at me
i don't care all right this is the thing
and so what we start to see with this
this modern neuroscience that uh the
people like emma gilkers come along and
it's actually really well studied and
it's like one of the most
solid things of all is that we have
inside of ourselves two
big chunks two big presences if you will
and you might not think it's that that
big of a deal it's like all right you
can tell me that that's all right but
there's this weird thing that
when people used to have epilepsy used
to cut the brains in half so if you
if you cut the the corpus callosum the
connector of the brains and let them
be themselves you can actually ask both
sides questions and they'll give you
different answers
all right so what is this telling us
through the evidence it's telling us
that inside your head
there are two people basically i'm going
to run with that now they would never
say that they would say shut up stefan
don't be jump at the conclusions
but of course maybe i'll have a bit of a
i'll have a bit of a uh
diatribe here about the nature of
science and philosophy and this this is
this is gonna be very triggering you
know science and the scientists and the
the the almighty lab code and their
their data gathering
capabilities most certainly important
but of course what
we finally see is the most important
role of the as nietzsche said the
philosopher of the future is to be able
to categorize this data
into useful categories that we're able
to use as descriptors and guiders what
the way we go forward and actually what
goes on with these two brains is very
much much related to that so
what we have right now is actually a
really well studied proof that the brain
has two sides and they do do different
things but we don't have anybody who's
able to make sense of it ian mcgill
chris did probably the best job so far
by saying
master and its emissary you've got one
side of the brain that acts as this sort
of
general and this other side of the brain
that acts as a sort of soldier
and so what the general does this is the
right brain will say is it tells the
soldier to go do things this would be
the left right
soldier go and uh go on facebook and
look through all your notifications
and that would be a meaningful activity
is what the general will say and then
the soldier does and gets all wrapped up
in that and then comes back out full of
dopamine gets all
wrapped up and then comes back out and
um i'm kind of bouncing through a lot of
things right now but i'll try to stick
as
solidly to the point of all is that when
you cut these two brains in half they
sort of have different presences it
seems like they do different jobs and
they talk different
suggesting that there's two forms of
consciousness in your head that are
not unified and then one of them is
one of them is is actually it looks it
looks like very very uh
shall we say unaware of the other one
and this is the one that is also the
most
related to what we would understand is
self-consciousness so this is starting
to look an awful lot like
what freud and young understood as the
ego and then this other one is starting
to look an awful lot of what they look
like as
the idea of the unconscious because then
they say that the unconscious has a sort
of
weird intelligence a weird ability to do
things
with intelligence that we didn't expect
and so what we
start to see when we start to look at
this stuff and i think this is the main
trust of a lot of the things i've been
talking about recently
is that the hard science is starting to
give us the data to almost
take what these guys like freud and
young and nietzsche were
throwing language at to try and make
sense of this phenomenological
experience inside of their head of
like voices coming in and all this type
of stuff and they're starting to give us
give us tools and say
this is going somewhere there's
something to this and now the science is
starting to show us that there most
certainly could be
now if we think about the modern
paradigmatic
perspective on the nature of the mind we
assume and this is sort of related to
this idea of the collective we assume
that we're all rational individuals that
just need to get presented the evidence
and then what's going to happen is that
we'll just adopt the right opinions
but of course freud and young were never
for that neither was nietzsche of course
but they got disproved because they
weren't scientific enough they were
artists now we have harder science
coming in suggesting even harder again
that it's like yeah those guys are
actually right on premise
and it starts to be extremely
explanatory towards everything that
we're seeing around ourselves
what's going on and so i guess that's
the crux of what i'm saying i notice in
the red book it starts the
the more i read the red book and the
more i read this stuff about left right
and right brian and emma gilchrist the
more i start to see
the relationship between how these two
things are married in some type of sense
i'll give you a very very quick example
and i think we could wrap it up there is
that um
for example the the the left brain the
soldier
is sort of deployed to do missions
emissary means missionary you know
deployed to do missions in the world and
the right brain is the guy with the big
perspective
that is able to see the big picture and
decide
what is important and meaningful for the
left brain and the problem the problem
in our head
which what goes on is like the left
brain the ego if you want gets too
caught up in its mission
and loses sense of the big picture
that's what the right brain has to do is
jump in and and shock it and grab it and
tell it no you're doing the wrong thing
come back on track
and there's this this is kind of weird
because the left brain is not really
aware that the right brain is there it's
very very strange
and so perhaps that experience of these
two sides of the brain talking to each
other remember that they're actually
really divided and really inhibited from
from acting on each other
perhaps that's close to what we could
understand as some instances of
stuff like psychotic breaks and some
instances of of um
how we understand like perhaps voices in
our heads and all this type of stuff
it's a very very weird stuff but
the thing is is that as weird as it is
there is some solid science to back it
up
it's it's what we get we get the the
romance and the dynamism
of jumping to crazy conclusions but also
we have
actually decent evidence now to say that
this is not just
freud and young studying empirically
their patients and drawing ridiculous
conclusions because they're all on
cocaine
or they're all like absolute psychosis
crazy bastards like jung was and then we
get some very very interesting stuff
from from here
and so perhaps what happened to young
was of course his right brain invading
his
egotistical left brain and setting him
off course and i would say that was my
spiel that is my stick
that's my stick currently where i'm at
right now i don't know what you just
make it out are you do you think i'm a
madman are you going to shout me out the
room
i don't know but there there you go i've
given i've given it all so
i i guess uh peter any thoughts all
right so if you have any questions start
throwing them in the chats
uh so the the title of this talk um
uh pandemic of groupthink do you have
any thoughts on that and like how this
how this may relate yes okay so
there is there is a huge relation to
this of course because the
the big first thesis the first principle
of the modernity of the way that we or
we organize our collective societies is
we have this
notion that we have uh all we need to do
is get presented the evidence and we
will rationally make the good the right
decisions we have this idea that our
brains are this one thing
and the problem with our brains is that
the right information has not been put
inside of them that's the thesis
all right you think about everything
that's going on right now and everything
in terms of like arguing and like
culture and all that type of stuff it's
this idea that people have the wrong
things in their head think even about
the idea of stuff like censorship
you're you're saying the wrong words we
need to put the right words into your
head and then you
all those bad emotions will go away all
right so there's this thesis
that you were just a united enlightened
soul and what goes into your head
information-wise is what determines your
head and what comes out of your head is
a signal of all that it's too it
sees you as a single thing this is the
enlightenment perspective
now what freud and young did is they
they subverted that this is why they're
such a big deal nietzsche did it first
really and they were suggesting that
there's this huge unconscious force
that you have to almost develop a
relationship with in order to develop
a complete character a complete
perspective a sophisticated perspective
now this is a huge problem because if
that's true
that means this thesis of how and
how it how we become individuals
responsible in society as
democratic and members to to guide
society towards the good
if if if we run with the thesis that
freud and young presented
that just can't work in the way that
we're doing it right now that cannot
work in the way they're doing it right
now because
the way education works where it's just
put in information the way politics
works where it's get the right
information
all of that is is completely against
what you freud and young are saying
it just does not work it does not
compute now of course that's been
ditched but this left brain right brain
stuff is now coming back to haunt us
and say there's a serious serious
suggestion
that uh this stuff is real and then what
we start to go down
is back to these psychoanalysts and we
start to see stuff like um
you know cognitive dissonance is very
famous that that people
have already decided what they want and
where they want to see things going
they've already decided their positions
based on emotional unconscious reasons
and there's no
reasoning with them there's no reasoning
and this is on all sides and either
sides
and we're kind of stuck in this spiral
where there'll be a lot of chatter
there'll be a lot of talk there'll be a
lot of the debating you know you go on
reddit you go on twitter you'll you'll
find plenty of debates
about people trying to like show
themselves the right information and all
that stuff but that's going to slowly
slow like that maybe very slowly will
will turn minds but
definitely not not as a whole and that's
kind of a scary thing to get into so
if we were to talk about a pandemic of
group think i wouldn't necessarily say
there's like
you know one bad perspective and all
that
although there's plenty of bad
perspectives out there but more that
there's a sort of psychological
underpinning a psychological
perspective underpinning this that's
putting us in a very scary place let's
put it that way
so i don't know does that answer your
question and um when we were chatting
uh before we're talking about you know
uh my area of interest the culture war
and stuff like that
and as i told you uh you know jordan
peterson was my therapist
uh before he became famous and it's
quite a weird thing seeing your
therapist become like a culture warrior
um do you think there's a reason why a
jungian and a
you know a psychotherapist went into the
culture war the way he did with his
analysis
oh it's a good question there's a good
that's a very good question actually
that's a very good question
i think um my understanding of jordan is
that
he was very very unconscious of this so
him and sam harris had a conversation
and right at the end of the whole thing
was crap to be honest in my opinion but
right at the end was the one of the most
lucid and beautiful moments of i've seen
in the
intellectual sphere in a long time and
uh sam and jordan were asked by douglas
murray it's like
what do you understand is i think it was
evil okay and so
sam kind of dribbled and tripped up and
all this type of stuff and it's like oh
that bad
i don't know he said something very very
very shallow and you could you could
almost
see that there was there was like it was
like a computer trying to give a
an informative answer you know what i
mean and then jordan like literally
paused for a moment and it was almost
like it was
in his voice there was this depth and
heaviness in his voice
and he he made some type of statement
and he knew inside of him he could like
basically
you know like the idea of like the
shadow you could hold down on someone's
neck and squeeze until they have no life
left
and he knew that he had that in him he
knew that there was a
absolute lion inside of himself that's
because that's what we are we're
monsters you know
we have that in us all of us do your
nervous system has that in you
now this i think exposed everything
because jordan was someone who was aware
that his ego his his little bubble up in
here of of rational consciousness that
goes about the day
that is not his entirety and the thing
that
drives a lot of his behavior is is
unconscious if you will is the
is in the nervous system or the right
brain whatever you want to call it
and then tied to that is is for example
the
the the the predator can come out when
you're in danger and kill someone if you
talk to someone who's ever
who's ever been in war they will post
traumatic stress they'll often say that
the experience is an outer body
experience what does that mean it feels
like you're watching yourself killing
people
what does that mean it's like your ego
suddenly lets go and lets the nervous
system do what the instincts are good at
doing
and it's good at killing stuff and then
suddenly you're you're you come back
home and you're you're in shock because
it's like i just murdered like 40 people
and i i didn't even do it something else
did it for me this is actually
really in alignment with how stuff like
uh traditional paganism works for
example odin was the god of the berserk
estate which is where the the viking
warriors would give themselves up
the odin's energy what was that well an
outer body experience where
odin takes over and he kills people and
he kills people for you he's the god of
war
it's a frightening thing the god of
frenzy it's a frightening thing but it's
the reality of what humanity is
and jordan peterson had a grip on that
and tied to that predator is also tied
to
negative feelings all right so i go
through my whole life
and like we live in a brilliant society
but that doesn't stop
you know rationally it's perfect all you
have to do is work hard and then you
reach the top rationally you're perfect
but but but people aren't rational and
the fact that there's people winning and
you're not winning
causes you to just get that little ounce
of envy and
and and anger and life is traumatizing
in a thousand different ways
and the trauma gets stored in your
nervous system i'm doing this now as a
as a psychologist yeah resentment
i'm doing this now as a psychologist i'm
like working with people and you see it
all the time
and it's so scary man because you sit
down with someone and you talk them
through
what happened to them there's a woman i
was just talking to recently you know
you're talking through what happened
she's telling you that she's just gone
through this mad divorce
okay and she's saying that she's dealt
with it and i talk her back into her
nervous system i talk her out of her
left brain or ego into her right brain
and she's rationally explained to me
that she's absolutely fine there's
nothing wrong with her
and i just talk her into it and i i'm
not telling her what to think i'm just
asking her to go there
and she just erupts crying because she's
really [ __ ] up still
she's not like like broken but she's
just like it's hard it's hard to go
through stuff like that
you take like 40 punches in the face and
stomach throughout like this long year
of going through a divorce
and you store all that in your nervous
system and you eventually get over it
you develop like
like your sort of ego to help you get
through it and that's not an ego and
like arrogance it's just like you know
your day to day to finish your to-do
list instead of breaking down crying all
the time but then
you kind of work into someone and it's
still there and it erupts it erupts like
energy
and that's the trauma you're picking up
that's the bad energy you're picking up
and we all pick it up i hate to say it
you know
and we store it in the unconscious
stored in the nervous system stored
under the right brain whatever you want
to say i don't care about the words
and jordan peterson i believe was was
aware that there's a lot of people out
there
picking up traumatic energy and there's
no psychological way
for them to expel that and when you
don't have a psychological
conception if you're stuck in the
rational enlightenment idea all you have
to do is think straight
you won't be able to get rid of that bad
energy and so what will happen is that
bad energy will
boil up inside of human as nietzsche
said it will fester into
horizontal mods and then what happens is
the bad and all emotions want to go in a
direction they all want to go somewhere
anger wants you to go and destroy
someone love wants you to go and make
love to someone
resentment wants you to go and destroy
someone as well and it all
collects together with a large group of
people who've got all this resentment
inside of them
and it starts to swa swell up in this
like group
and it's just floating there like this
dark cloud and all it takes is one
person to walk over and paint a little
picture and say that's the person who
calls that or that's the archetype you
know the archetype of the
the capitalist or whatever you want to
say that's the person who calls that
this
giant storm cloud of anger
swirls on top of that it's like a magic
spell and then you've got what
40 million people who want to murder a
certain type of person
and that's when you're in a scary place
that's when you're in like you know the
the the crazy stuff that happened during
the 20th century and all that
and it's that simple it starts from that
level and so i think that that's a long
answer to your question but i think
that's why jordan peterson was so
relevant okay
yeah that's good um okay let's pivot to
the
uh the chats uh david swedlow you had a
similar question
yeah i was curious if um if you what
what do you think about the thought that
young may be
more popular now because we're in a
similar kind of war
pre-madness certainly madness of pre-war
kind of
something's happening we see we see the
kind of the meaning crisis is coming
home
right and so in a sense um what young
was dealing with was
similar you know so there's something
about that you know
i'm curious about it i'm curious to hear
you talk about that a little bit
a hundred percent i think this pandemic
is very very interesting for a lot of
people because
again i it comes down to um how much
energy we all give to
things like twitter and reddit and i've
i've got caught it up in this as well
you know you go in and you're trying to
tell people like
like oh this is where you're not correct
and like i have these rational opinions
that you should really listen to because
i've got good information
and you think about what's going on
there is that there's this conversation
going on
we're doing the democratic thing which
is you know it's good good intentions
and we're trying to explain to ourselves
like the correct way to see the world
but you'll quickly come to this idea
that
most people have first principles that
are emotionally charged that they're
never going to move from
and the thing that actually moves first
principles and this is this is this is a
very very sad thing about human
realities
is is pain it's trauma is
strong emotions shock right and you see
this on an individual level when you
have someone
who believes that as a kid the world is
all a good place and then their parents
split up
suddenly a shock wave hits them that can
last in their nervous system
30 40 years and can haunt them like a
depression
very very strong evidence for that
depression is very very tight
schizophrenia very very tied to
childhood trauma
okay and it kind of hits you in that
type of vibe
and you're you're stuck and you've
you've got this this bad
energy inside you and we go up and we
think that we can talk rationally on
twitter but then
what's actually gonna it's gonna take to
change the conversation is a hit
of bad energy to shake people to wake
people up
and you know you can you you'll see for
example you'd see a lot of people
say stuff like uh you don't like i think
there's this thing with ben shapiro and
piers morgan a while ago
and i'm not really a big fan of ben
shapiro but and there's this thing where
he i think they're talking about guns
and i think pierce morgan is saying
something like
do you really think the government would
try to like
hurt you are you insane are you insane
and then and then all this stuff happens
and i'd say like
i think guns in america are just like
flying off the shelves right now so you
can see
the people of all of a sudden like the
perspective has changed
and that wasn't people oh listen to ben
shapiro and be like yeah
he was right rationally he got him there
it was because this shock wave of fear
hit the entire population on a huge and
you could feel it in the air it was
actually a crazy time
and i'm not even sure if we're out of it
or whatnot and
what was so interesting about young's
red book is that i he it's almost like
he got hit with that shockwave
maybe a year before everybody else did
which was world war one
and that's a weird idea it's like how
how does someone get hit early before
it's happened
i don't know maybe if you're spending a
lot of time with patients and talking to
them about their dreams and the dreams
or
i don't know super super computer mind
is
putting all this stuff together you hear
about it early but
it's a very very weird thing and this is
you know where things get a bit loose
but still it's very hard to say that
young was wrong
a war did kick off so he kind of got
that one right
and of course what you noticed in maybe
the last year or so like
things went from like even the internet
is such an interesting thing the
internet started as this
funny place where the memes are very
innocent but then maybe in the last like
four years five years
things got like really heavy and dark
and now they're starting to get almost
like
scary i think there's almost like uh
around about trump's election
things were sort of like funny if you
know what i mean there was a lot of kind
of like
joking going on and it was like very
light-hearted and it was like all
internet wars and there's no real
consequences to all this
but now i there's this heavy energy to
it where it's like oh my god there's
something very serious happening
like we're in history again and um
yeah i would assume that uh like
whatever's going on with young it would
be
tied to that thinking
that's very very interesting um because
there is like compared to like you said
that 2016 elections
they were you know it's intense but it
was a little jokey but now it's
dark you know this is [ __ ] dark and
it's
really interesting what you said kind of
like the weather vein of these
psychotherapists who can kind of pick up
on it
um because i did a lot of dream analysis
with peterson about my own dreams we
talked a lot about the culture
stuff before he went into it uh in his
practice
and he did feel like he spoke a
primordial language being plugged into
that that kind of the dream world
so this is very fascinating
[Music]
my medic keeper you had a question
yeah um do you think the
unconscious should remain unconscious or
should we strive to reveal it to
ourselves
is this maybe the final piece of the
enlightenment project
it's a good question excuse the burp i
think that was my unconscious making me
burp it's
saying shut up and don't tell the
management that that that could have
been it
and so i i would i would assume
i would run with the the like oh look
i'm going to try actually reframe this a
little bit because this is where i think
a lot of
the jungian stuff and gets in the way
because
what i see with the neuroscience all
right is that you have a left brain and
a right brain you have your brain split
in half
and they have two different functions
and i'm forgiving me that i'm not
explaining this in comprehensive detail
like it isn't kind of a new thing but
it's but it's important
it's a really important thing and um
yeah i'm kind of doing a bit of a
botched job but think of it like a
general and a soldier
so the the general has the plan the big
picture but he doesn't actually go in
the field and do anything
and so your ego is the thing that goes
in the field we're full of dopamine and
does stuff but of course
sometimes the the soldier can get lost
he doesn't know what he's doing he's no
big picture
and he ends up doing the wrong thing he
ends up like going on facebook all day
and like arguing about politics right
when he could probably be better off
just like i don't know establishing a
firm if he was that worried or
actually going out and like healing his
relationships with his family you know
there's their better better missions if
you
want to say and and so what we what i
would understand is the unconscious is
actually
this this development of a relationship
like literally it starts with an
understanding it's like all right
first of all your head is split in half
at the very least right so you got to
have this understanding of how to
stop this ego and get it talking to the
other part of your head
now dreams are a great way to subvert
that because it's instantly like all
right there's another part of your head
that makes
complex stories at night that you don't
do
so that's that's one that's just on on
the table the the quote unquote right
brain it seems to have quite a lot of
those characteristics as well and i
would assume
that if you want to say to someone how
to use your head properly well you've
got two sides to do two
specific roles and the problem that
often comes is that they fracture
and they lose coordination so certainly
i think we should
we should try to integrate the
unconscious as young might say young i
think gives you procedural ways that you
can do this you know
go into your emotions right brain more
connected with your sense-based
experience
go into your emotions go feel all that
type of stuff get more connected with
your body get more connected with the
people around you
pay attention your dreams pay attention
to your thoughts pay attention to the
things that
pay attention to how you have a little
voice in your head that rationalizes
these complex stories about
the meaning of the world to you and
that's probably a load of crap that you
need to subvert
you know so i certainly think that that
should be done
because it's about using our heads
correctly it's about using the division
of our brain correctly it's about
playing
with what we are we're designed to work
a certain way don't try
force yourself to be rational
enlightenment ego when you're not
that's that's a mistake so i would
certainly say and
definitely do this definitely do this
now did you have a second part of that
question i can't remember what it was
no no no all right
all right um nicole you're up next
awesome uh hi so my question is very
much
it's related to the question that was
just asked before so i just wrote it
here so i'll read it
and then i'll kind of um i'll touch on
my own personal experience with this
just slightly to give it some context
um so i've uh recently
heard someone say that to fully immerse
oneself in union psychology is to move
through the world
in a way sort of as a schizophrenic does
where everything
is sort of imbued with meaning and
everything can be interpreted
as a sign for your unconscious telling
you something
um is this an accurate portrayal of
understanding oneself through union
frame
and then like the second part of that
was just like through my own personal
experience i kind of had like a wake-up
moment
recently where i realized that i feel
that i'm doing that like too much
that i'm kind of like moving the world
in the way really like
if everything truly does have meaning um
that can just like overwhelm you with
trying to understand everything
and then if that's not the case then
what are those
signs or what are those moments of
realization and what aren't
i'm i'm gonna wreck thank you thank you
very much nicole for your question i'm
gonna wreck all your heads with some of
the answers i'm gonna give to this stuff
because i'm gonna keep defaulting into
this left brain right brain stuff it's
gonna become frustrating
but um it's not for no reason because
what is so interesting about the nature
of these two hemispheres
is that this left brain as i said the
soldier that goes out and do
does your to-do list wired full of
dopamine more dopamine receptors over
here so it gets you to do stuff
it gets you to get caught up in the
plants all right and it's it's
very prone if a soldier loses connection
with its general it's very prone to
the panic and it's like i gotta do this
i gotta do this it loses sense of the
big picture
it it makes all these elaborate plans
it's really good at making elaborate
plans and steps and all this type of
stuff but it doesn't have a big picture
perspective at all all right and so this
is this is one of its highly common
problems with this type of stuff your
ego your left brain you get caught up
in these silly little plants i do it all
the time it's like i'll do
50 videos in this topic and i'll plan
them all out and then i only ever get
like one or two done that type of thing
you know you just get too caught up in
this type of stuff your little little
perspective is trying to to figure out
the whole world fit the whole world
inside your ego and start your left
right inside the soldier's
little plan that's what he's trying to
do he's trying to fit a whole war inside
the soldier's little plan
now what this right hemisphere does and
this is so weird about it is that you
could actually understand it as like the
general
and the general has like all this
information coming he's got all the
intelligence agencies and all this he
gets
all this information into him and
actually the way this works for you is
your right brain does this with your
senses your nervous system
and weirdly the way you can understand
the right brain is like a woo-woo
you know like you go into yogi you see
the woo-woo girl yoga teacher he's like
everything's energy man
like it's all just energy and that's
literally what this this right brain is
like it's
in connection with the world it feels
the world it's it's completely like
enriched with the world a lot more than
this this left brain it has the bigger
sense of the world a bigger sense it's
like the i say um
i've said before it's like the the
general who's weird to all the soldiers
he goes up and he picks up all the
the mud and rubs between his uh and
smells it and you're like what is he
doing
but it's it's special to him it's he has
a sense of things he has a connection of
things or her whatever you want to think
and then this idea i think of when we
have these
breaks from the ego when the ego at the
left frame whatever it gets subverted it
realizes it's not alone in its head
it the right brain comes back online and
it's it's kind of shocking because
everything is connected it's it's
it feels everything and this can be
incredibly overwhelming as i said
your nervous system you store all these
emotions and someone tells themself
i've gotten through a divorce and you
baby step them back into the felt
experience of their body
where they've stored all this and then
it comes up and it can
freak them out it can be such a shock
because they're full of pain
they're full of pain and it all erupts
and they have to feel it all again and
that's probably the hardest thing
but of course this is what i believe
young men by the anima is that or the
animus whatever you want to call it
is that when you let this part of
yourself erupt and
you you allow yourself to feel your
reality again because reality is full of
pain so you don't actually want to feel
it
when you let yourself feel your reality
again this is where you start to get
this sort of feeling of
full of meaning of connected with
everything that type of thing
and i certainly think there's decent
evidence for this you know
so i i encourage people to integrate the
unconscious and get back in touch with
this type of stuff
and think like maybe study this right
brain stuff and understand what would be
perhaps more right brain things that you
can balance out your
your left brain work with and all this
stuff because ultimately they're
supposed to work together
but um i would i would highly encourage
people to um
to to operate in that type of sense like
understand that
of all things the world is is full of
meaning
not in not in any way that your left
brain ego will be able to figure out you
can't just categorize and make a big
plan and make a big model of the
universe that makes sense
the world is full of energy and energy
is actually what gives meaning to your
not
to your life young called it numenosity
you know
it it it makes things matter to you do
you see the way people pick up stones
and they're like
precious little stones and all this type
of stuff and and i think that's actually
the
the more human way to coordinate
yourself that's the type of thing i
i i know i'm kind of getting off track a
little bit here but that's the type of
way you could coordinate yourself is
understand that it's it's more about
relationships it's more about
felt relationships with the world it's
more about developing a
not an intellectual categorization of
the world that makes sense because
that's
never going to work in the way that
you're trying to do it but on almost
building a a a connected energetic
bridge to the world
and then as you said that that starts to
sound an awful lot like schizophrenia
but of course
of course if you check out my last video
and look through until about 40 minutes
i start talking about
the schizophrenia and the relationship
to this dynamic that i'm talking about
and it's
incredibly interesting how all this
stuff connects so
i'm sorry i couldn't answer more
comprehensively but uh there does my
take
thank you very much cool um
alyssa you had a question
yes hi um there are many who claim that
a collective projection of the father
archetype is being placed upon jordan
peterson
this has allowed jordan to stand on the
positive end of the archetypal spectrum
guiding others in cleaning up their life
and bringing order to chaos but has also
resulted in a huge backlash as a
representative of the patriarchal system
what is your take is peterson utilizing
his insights of young to speak to the
collective consciousness
oh it's a good take as well that's a
good take as well it's a good question
and questions lead to good takes is what
i should be saying
and so it's very very interesting
question like did did is he
i i don't think you're necessarily
saying this but does he become a cult
leader does he become the
the daddy of the millennials and um
again what i was saying about him
earlier is that he digs into the
unconscious
and he he realizes that like you know he
he just
sort of feels that there's all these
people full of trauma and he can see it
in his classroom they're coming in and
they're
they're they're like really really
really really upset and they have this
upset and aggressive tone
and they're they're starting to turn
into what he might understand as a
collective movement and a collective
movements are almost always formed by
collective emotions and anguishes and
pains
if you study collective movements you'll
see that at root there's very little
rationale behind them it's almost
always a felt problem and a desperate
oppression or injustice and whatnot
now of course he tapped into that trauma
and felt that and he knew that this was
coming and
look where we are now but of course he
also tapped into
the the the lost boys as they call them
you know the people who
are are looking for something and you
could feel this energy it was everywhere
it's still here by the way
it's not like that has not been solved
at all and there's a lot of people who
are
looking for someone to give order and
shape and direction
and if you're sort of going in that
right brain mode and feeling and you're
talking to a lot of people and you'll
feel
out a lot of people that they their
lives are a disaster they can't put
stuff together and there's a lot of
people who are
who are whose lives fall apart and they
get hit by trauma and then they turn
resentful
and then there's a lot of people whose
lives fall apart and they wish that
there was some way that they could put
their lives back together and so in some
sense jordan starts to speak in the
opposite direction
he gives you the answer to resentment
which is to you know
put yourself together and clean your
room and all that type of stuff it's
brilliant advice
and of course what we would start to do
is then project him as like a a guide a
moses i don't necessarily think
father i think moore's in terms of like
uh he had that prophetic energy which is
father like of course but he sort of
that's what he was sort of like the guy
pointing for a direction do you know
what i mean
and this is why i think his criticism
was so intense and religious is because
he was someone who was giving people a
way up a purpose and a meaning and a
belief that there is a way that's
fundamentally it there is a way forward
i can do something and all that type of
stuff and that em allows them to deal
with these horrible feelings that a lot
of people are
are turning our joining movements for
you know and i think that actually comes
down to
and quite quite a lot of the foundation
of what he was trying to do
thank you thank you
all right um chris you had a question
if you're going to meet yourself yeah
yeah i'll just uh
read this here um i said i'm not so
convinced anymore that rationalization
is the problem of modernity christian
scholastics drew a lot from greek
philosophical tradition
such as thomas aquinas being the
christian scholastic not the greek
philosopher obviously
and stated that one could know the truth
of a god through reason
alone although there is also a component
of faith
that has to exist within christianity
for the actual christian narrative
of course modernity seems to be
descending
into an irrational state where there is
a denial of universal morality
and an affirmation of relativity and
thus a denial of logos
thoughts stefan it's a great question as
well
all right so i'm going to talk a little
bit about the naughtiest nasty german
incel we've ever heard of
naughty nasty nietzsche and he um he
he's the type of guy that you read
through and you're just scratching your
head because
he doesn't like socrates for example he
likes socrates but he thinks he's wrong
and you're kind of like socrates is like
the famous philosopher made philosophy
how can you not like socrates like
what's that what are you doing nietzsche
you're kind of going a bit crazy here
and he's like yes i am
and then nietzsche proposes that
socrates was
the sign of the greek people
degenerating into a fallen state and
you're like
what you're on about man what really and
so the basic thesis here is that
when your instincts are strong when
you're in a good shape you can actually
be extremely
rational irrational when your instincts
are are strong
you don't need the truth the truth is
useless in some sense
his example and this is this is going to
trigger a lot of people is that you know
the christians
don't have an accurate view of the world
in in nietzsche's opinion
and but they took over the world and it
was more because like the people the
germanic people who were carrying it had
these like
horrible intense you know world
conquering energies they ruled europe
you know
and they ruled the irish you know the
english germanic people ruled england
and ireland and they were world
conquerors they they could do their
strong instincts
and over a long period of time what
happens is those instincts get
weak and you get out of your body and
you kind of float up into
reason and you start to overthink what's
going on and it's like the way that like
you could be a massive hypocrite but if
you're winning that's all that matters
there's a lot of um game theory things
they show where you know they'll make
little
digi robots that like understand the
truth and robots that just
try to get to the next level of the game
the ones that go and try to evolve and
get to the next level destroy the ones
that want the truth all the time
consistently you know it's very very
basic idea the truth is not that
valuable
and so what happens then with this scary
thought is that
when your instincts get weak your reason
comes in to try help you
explain what's happening and so
nietzsche is saying that
what you see with socrates is that
moment where the greeks these were the
people who made greek mythology probably
the most sophisticated
religious system bar perhaps
judeo-christianity
you know unbelievably so beautiful that
even people like freud and young used it
for the majority of
our conceptions like edipulat narcissist
and their instincts got weak
they lost their instincts and so this
this this thinking came in to be a big
thing oh let's let's
sit around and think about what we're
doing now pause wait there for a second
let's sit around and think about what
we're doing it's like if you if you
trust your instincts you don't you never
think
you know i think the the virgin chad
mean the chad never thinks he just does
that's the type of thing you're just a
man of action type of vibe
and so they all become like you know
virgin socrates oh
pause for a second let's let's figure
out what's going on and of course
of course they the second socrates shows
up and then they're all trying to figure
out what's going on
you have only a couple hundred years
later well basically you have alexander
de gray who swoops down and takes over
all of greece
and then you have the romans who come in
and just say oh the really good
philosophy guys how about we slap a
roman uh
roman spork flag on it and then we'll
you can keep doing your philosophy there
in the corner
and we'll rule you and you can be the
philosophers how about that type of life
and so um reason or reasoning or
rationalizing and of course if you look
at left brain right brain you'll find
that the
the sort of voice in your head
rationalizing part of yourself seems to
have
the centralization in the the hyper
conscious right
left brain the ego if you will which is
again a very very scary thing
and then yeah so that that's all seems
like a signal of
falling and so as as nietzsche would go
on to say that
of course as you're saying this whole
journey between socrates
and christianity and nietzsche would
even accuse christianity like he's a big
fan of christ we didn't even accuse
christianity of
stuffing all our elite thinkers into
little uh churches that are promoting a
philosophy of anti-body anti-life
anti-instincts
which means that we further fall up into
our head which actually
ironically leads to this brilliant laser
focus on
abstract thinking very left-brained
which actually creates science
which then through the laser focus of
science turns back on the religion
and starts to question its its own
reality which actually just
exposes the religion as irrational and
then destroys it and then puts us in the
goddess dead state
and this whole arc would like the the
the ability to see that is
unbelievable this whole story then leads
up to the point where we're at now
and of course what i think young did is
young sits down and if you read about
the red book and the anima which spoke
to him this is where it comes from
he noticed that he was sitting there and
a voice came and started to talk to him
but he realized that aquinas had a voice
that spoke to him the voice of reason
and the voice of logos if you will but
young saw it as a female woman
a girl a chick you know the the e-girl
coming up being like yo
young what's up and he understood this
is his felt
experience coming up and amazingly when
you study left brain right brain as i
was saying earlier right brain more
connected with the energetic world and
felt experience
young's conception might be more
accurate and that's a weird weird thing
to what we understand now young might
have been more in touch
with the correct intuitive understanding
of the psychology you have an animating
voice
inside you that's not rational it's
instinctive
and this ties a lot with nietzsche's
nietzsche's assertion that we need to
develop a relationship not with a
rational truth
but a will to power an animating energy
if you want to think about it that way
and this is where anime comes from
the roman word for soul which means
animation
animal animation animosity all those
things are tied together
and it's a very very very very very
interesting way of thinking
so thanks for the question good question
yeah thank you
so we got we got a lot of uh interesting
questions um
how are you for time dance because i
have someone on but i'm able to push
them back if
you've got a lot of stuff uh we have 10
minutes i want to sneak in
one more question yeah um
would you like to admit yourself
okay well peter can you just read it
so i just i don't have the chat open
here so it might be faster
sure okay do you believe in
left-handedness to be associated with
more
uh systemic connections with higher
speed of both hemispheres as suggested
by
ian mciltrust uh i think that's a
pronounced name if so
any ideas uh regarding why that is
why that not to become evolutionary
dominant any practical ways to build
that connection
uh systematically i've been i've been
exposed i've been exposed i actually
don't know
about that side of things at all i have
no idea what that is and i'll have to
look it up but but thank you for the
question i'm afraid i won't be able to
give you a good answer on that
um i i would assume that there's a sort
of way that you could perhaps train
these parts of your head to talk to each
other and there'd be different
characteristics with each of them like
for example
our language center is the broca's area
and wernicke's area is on the left side
and so that says a lot about like the
words and voice and meaning and all that
type of stuff but of course the right
hemisphere has
the the musical sense of language on its
side as well and that's of course
important things and i'd imagine there's
ways
that you can train your brain and the
whole left hand right hand thing is very
interesting and of course the more you
study this stuff and then think about
how
and many institutions like the the
church or even in soviet union they used
to force you to use your
your right hand even if you're a
left-hander it's all really really
interesting stuff
but i'm not able to give you a good
answer i'm afraid
all right um so you have something right
at the hour so
you're cool to go into that like i'm
loose i'm loose man yeah okay
um so i'm going to read this question
on else behalf so how does your
left right framing interact with shadow
work like
internal family systems with its various
parts uh
managers protectors exiles uh seems
re-evaluating and re-establishing
relationships is fundamental it's a
really good question all right
so i'm a bit a bit of a noob like i'm
getting exposed here all sides like i
don't have a sort of a
a total conception of like how you apply
this stuff to therapy i do
i do default go to ian mcgill chris look
at young stuff from this lens it's
brilliant jordan peterson's another
great example of course
but if i was to give you an answer to
what you're asking and the left brain
it has a this is so interesting about it
all right
so the soldier when he's in the trench
the way that he he convinces himself to
take the next step the soldier is the
left brain is the ego the way he
convinces himself to take that step he
gets to use kick of dopamine
that's the next goal all right and when
something gets in the way of the next
goal he gets angry
yeah that that that feels normal listen
that you want to go on facebook and look
at your dopamine things and get angry
now getting to the end of an argument is
also a goal and so when you're you're
writing on
on discord or reddit or something like
that and you're saying i think this
and i can't believe that you don't think
that you feel anger kicking in this is
of course someone getting in the way of
your left brain getting its dopamine
kick
and so you are not rationally prone to
having rational conversations with
people
you are full of this monstrous
egotistical left brain
that wants to just get angry at people
and prove them wrong and and
have crazy fights and this is not wrong
this is not a a silly thing the soldier
sometimes needs to kill people
but if the soldiers running around just
like you know shooting civilians and all
this type of stuff then you have a bit
of an issue
and so you you perhaps could come in
with this idea that of course this
the anger the debating the resentment
that it's your fault or this little
story that we all have among each other
this is what um freud noticed that
there's the families are almost like
these webs
of crap that are just so hard to get out
of and sometimes it's better to just
leave for a while and then come back you
know and kill your father and all that
type of stuff
symbolically and now of course this
right brain thing has a very very
interesting take on um how you relate
with people because it's better at
relationships
it's the part of yourself that feels
relationships it's the part of yourself
it seems
to be more dominant with stuff like
empathy it's obviously
the part of yourself that senses stuff
it's the part of yourself that can
recognize emotions and faces
when someone gets right hemispheric
damage they can't
properly understand faces or emotions
all this type of stuff
and so if we're to talk about stuff like
relationships my god it's
all keyed into this other side of the
head if you know what i mean
and there's one dude if you've gone to
my channel his name is uh i think we say
from
from atheist to peterson the christ and
it's duke of lazalo
and he um he went through all this you
know he went back to his
his family and he spent a lot of time
sort of like reconnecting with him in an
energetic way and
and humility was his big virtue he
turned very christian
and it put aside you know the kind of
resentment and the anger and all that
type of stuff
and allowed him to just reconnect like
literally his goal was just i i want to
reconnect i don't want you to be correct
i don't want to know what you think
about all this type of
type of stuff i just want to develop an
energetic connection to you i know it's
as woo
as it can get but it fundamentally is
like changing his life right now
and perhaps that's the the model that
you can go for a lot of the problems
with our families is that they're
rational intellectual
and there's a great amount of distance
and there's a lot of unsaid stories that
are kind of getting in the way and
angers and all this type of stuff and so
perhaps that could be a way to subvert
it
i hope that's good enough all right
beautiful
uh so we're approaching the hour um i
think it'd be prudent to uh
end here unless you there's one more
question just came in um maybe we can
just jump to it
uh kevin deland do you want to ask your
question
sure hiya boyo um
i'm wondering how the emotional
experiences of what you call the right
brain
soldier can affect the rational
strategies
of say the left brain in general and
could there be
so um like could there could it end up
that there are competing interests
um one framework that i sort of
mentioned in the chat i'm not sure
from you're familiar with it was um like
an artificial intelligence
cognitive science named marvin minsky
who thought of the mind as like a
society of mind and one example he uses
is the child wants to
like build a tower of blocks and he also
wants to destroy the tower of blocks so
when he's building it or maybe the
destroyer part of
like the agent in his mind convinces the
builder to like you know build a tower
and then when he's building the tower
there might be conflicting
sort of yeah like he might want to he
might want to knock him down but he also
might want to build it bigger so i'm
wondering your take on
how sort of the emotions of the soldier
can affect
the rational strategies of the left
brain general and then how
the many generals in your head can sort
of duke it out yeah it's a very good
question there's this weird um
this is that's very sort of freudian
where uh you have the
the the self-sabotage issue so it's like
i want to become
famous and why do you want to become
famous so that you can you know act
out the sort of hidden drama inside your
soul where you want to like you know
prove your your mother wrong by
embarrassing yourself in front of the
family and so you become famous and then
you get
drunk and end up naked on the street for
the press or something like this
and there's like this weird conflicting
thing where you think that you're doing
this big drama to get to this top for
some magical reason but really it's
about
giving you the power to act out some
other darker desire and all this type of
stuff
and i think um i think there is is
decent suggestions that perhaps
like well for example these two parts of
your head i i
i'm i'm kind of speculating a bit but
they most certainly can have different
intentions and wills
and i think this is what this idea of
the right brain putting in
and kicking and like you know the
soldier goes off crazy and starts
shooting up a town
when he should be on a mission and so
the general flies in in his truck
and says what are you doing you crazy
stop come back
he beats him up he punishes him or
whatever that type of thing like
perhaps that's what a sort of psychotic
break is for some people in
general in a speculative way and then
that would suggest then that there's
sort of two intentions going on what's
so weird
about the right brain the left brain's
full of dopamine the right brain is full
of anxiety receptors
so you can imagine that the soldier is
going and doing something but underneath
it
you've definitely had this experience
you're on facebook and you're you're the
little soldier going after the dopamine
spirals
smashing away telling people how they're
all wrong owning everyone all right
and then underneath that this big
negative mood starts to build
because you know in if you zoomed out
and took a big perspective on what
you're doing
you would know that it's it's like
pathetic behavior and you hate yourself
doing it and so this sort of big mood
builds up and you can almost see there
that like
despite the fact that you're caught up
in what you're doing there's a sort of
negative
feeling getting built up is that perhaps
the right brain trying to do trying to
re-correct you is that the general sort
of sending you a lot of bad messages
being like stop what you're doing dude
this this
sucks this is pointless this is bad this
type of thing and i most certainly think
that's possible most certainly think
that's possible
and then it's like in terms of
experience yes i've seen it
happen loads of times it's happened to
me loads of times it's very very common
yeah
awesome so um let's end there before the
hour um
my friend any kind of closing thoughts
for us that place we can find you or
oh yeah well definitely check out the
old uber boyo channel i think a lot of
people would like perhaps to watch the
video on
the red book did young go schizophrenic
that's usually a great place to start
because i
sort of fast forward through a lot of
this stuff there and
ian mcgill chris is a fantastic big time
and
in terms of putting this into procedural
practice yes like absolutely
carlos gustavus young is a great stuff
as well
and um thank you very much for the
opportunity sir and thank you everybody
for
all the questions it's been lovely
beautiful so i'll make some
closing announcements in a moment but uh
my friend thank you again for coming to
the stawa
thanks everyone for their excellent
questions definitely check out his
youtube channel it's pretty
awesome um upcoming events we've got
another youtube personality superstar
coming in
um at 6 p.m eastern time today memes
reality and the occult
with chris gabriel who does meme
analysis
you can check that out there at the link
um and then
tomorrow we have a bunch of cool events
one of them spiritual mission of america
and the anthropocene and this is a
matt siegel he's a integral leftist he's
going to come in and talk about uh
that subject that should be pretty cool
you can check out
a website for more events our patreon
and our sub stack for
daily updates that being said everyone
thanks so much for coming to the store
today